Hi, I'm going to present the interpreter specifications. The slides were mostly done by Robin, so thank
you. We have a website, specs.ipfs.tech. Very nice. There's a QR code. And it looks like
this. We have some basic specifications for now. We only have the architecture, meta specifications,
HTTP gateways, and the IPNS specifications, which might get updated soon.
So why did we do this? Why standards? Well, it should be possible to implement something
without having to look at Kubo and other things. In the long term, documentation will be better
than code, because code might have bugs, might not be clearly readable for everyone, so documentation
is always good. We will also be able to maintain a clear track record of everything that all
the consensus, all the decisions that were made, and we will also support better test
writing. For example, for the gateway, we already have some work in progress for the
conformance test that Pietro talked about yesterday. And yeah, it's also a good way
to make it clear to bridge to other systems. So what are the goals of this very small project?
Well, small in size for now, but it's going to be big, we hope. Project, well, to look
good and give visibility to the specifications, because before this, they were just in a repository,
marked on files. It's not something nice to look at, and people are not going to look
for it. And if we have a website, it's easier, and it's an easier way to reference the specifications.
But at the end of the day, we keep it simple. It's still mostly marked down. It has some
add-ons that are specified, by the way, and it has table links and reference management,
and we support the typical specification features, such as definition references, the keywords
from the RFC 2119. And yeah, we will be progressively adding more tooling in order to make it better.
So if you want to participate in this project, you can see the repository for the specifications
at ipfs.specs.generator, which is ipfs.spec.generator. How creative. And you can read the specs for
specs, which is mostly marked down with some additions. Or you can also just copy-paste
some spec and figure it out. And you can just run makewatch, and it will work. And yeah,
that was a very short talk. So we're now on track again.
What do you need?
What do I need?
It's all done. You don't need any help. What's next?
Write more specs.
Dark mode.
What's that?
We had dark mode, but it was not very good, so we had to remove it before releasing it.
Coming soon.
Yes.
We'll bring it back.
We're waiting for your answers on what's coming. Is there any additions to the site that you're
planning? Is there any additions to the site that you're planning to make?
Yes, there's some updates we want to move. We want to add the IPIPs, which Lydell is
going to talk about in a minute. There's some other tweaks to make to the website, but it's
mostly working well. And add more specs.
Can the same spec generator be used outside of IPIP?
Yes, that's the goal.
We're in talks about using that to do specs.libp2p. I think probably next week we're going to
start working on that. I also have a code thing to bring out of storage about using
that for multi-formats. We'll see how that intersects with the ITF thing. If IPLD, IPNI
want to put their specs on this, this is meant to be generic, so we can absolutely reuse
it. And the working group can work on the spec for specs and help everyone get this
moving along.
I was kind of wondering that. Should the working group working group also be a place that's
surfacing where all the different specs are?
We're keeping the name. I should shut up some days.
I don't think that the working group working group needs to do a list of specs. I think
we can have a list of spec sites. My thinking was to basically in the footer of all these
things have a web ring kind of thing for those who are old enough to remember. So that everyone
can have their own theme and their own community for each segment, but also they are all tied
together.
Awesome. Thank you.