Okay, hey everyone! I minimally prepared for this because of things, but we are so excited
to announce IPFS Camp 2023 as we talked about. And we decided on Bangalore, India, November
3rd through 5th. And so super excited about that. But the purpose of this kind of workshop
discussion time is to really focus on bringing in more people who are interested in helping
us gather content for IPFS Camp and help build the organizing team. And so we could do a
quick retro of IPFS Camp from last year. We did one briefly, but it'd be just to refresh
our recollection of what we thought went well and what didn't go well and what we'd like
to have for next year.
So we thought we could do it, one way of doing this is I have this slide, I'll share it in
our general Slack. We could all use these stickies. I haven't shared the link yet, I'll
just do it right after. We could use the stickies to sort of take inputs from everyone sitting
over here, do the retro, followed by what are our goals and objectives, and then followed
by brainstorming what tracks do we want. But this is a way of doing this. If anyone here
has a better idea, we are open to that. Otherwise, I'll share the link right away and we can
get started.
Cool. So the box over there links to the recap blog. If you just want to give yourself a
quick refresh on what happened at IPFS Camp last time, maybe take a look at that blog.
We'll wait for about five minutes. And yeah, you all can just like input, pick one of those
stickies and put your thoughts and then we will discuss.
Okay, cool. I will do a quick recap of maybe let's fix things first and respond to a couple
of them that we already know we can. Yeah, Lisbon was 14 days. This one's not going to
be 14 days. It'll be three days of IPFS Camp. Plus this is not yet announced, but two days
of Phil Bangalore and maybe one more day, but that's about it. But this is it, like
seriously. However, we do expect that once we start promotions for IPFS Camp, other events
locally might come up as like side events around the same duration. So just FYI. But
I doubt it will be 14 days this time. So I do not doubt that it will not be 14 days this
time. And cool. More hacking time together, more workshops plus bounties. I think they
are both like similar, so I'll put them close to each other. More intro to IPFS talks. Yeah,
I think that's very relevant given the audience we will have. Implementers, builders, but
few users represented. Get NFT platforms. Okay. More substantial job fair, longer expo
and better scholars programming. Okay. And in the good things, lightning talks track,
giving back to the local community. Things content. We did some things content, include
that and recruit more contributors. 450 people. Oh, this time we'll definitely have more people.
Lip P2P track was great. Super well attended. And multiple tracks for beginners plus. Okay,
cool. Beatbox guy, we'll definitely have some equivalent entertainment version for that.
Okay, cool. I think this is great. And with this in mind, maybe let's think about what
are the broad goals and objectives we want to accomplish with IPFS camp this year. Probably
keeping in mind the keynote summary we saw yesterday on how can actually IPFS camp help
sort of magnify the outcomes of the action items we decided on yesterday. Yeah. Let's
maybe keep this to three minutes plus two minutes in case people want to expand.
I think one of the things that we saw at last IPFS camp was a lot of new people. And we
had some content for new folks, but even that, a lot of the feedback was that even that was
still too high of a barrier for them to climb and very, very technical for the level at
which they were entering. So I think a really clear path for very new beginner people, maybe
even folks who are learning how to code like a separate small track for that level of people
that are getting involved doing their first application or first web app, things like
that with IPFS.
Yeah. In very much the same vein, I mean, I think it's sort of like the same brainwave,
but that like one thing that I often find difficult to explain to people, and I think
that reflects on the same thing is like, what is this whole space? What are the things that
you can be doing with it? And so sort of like the 30,000 feet view of everything, and maybe
this is how you choose your own adventure in this space is something that could help
onboard people.
Yeah, I think riffing on that, I ended up putting philosophy of IPFS up there. Like,
what are we trying to do rather than just another weird system to make a web app with?
And that maybe links well with the like, get more nodes running as well. So those two could
be fitting together. Because ideally, and maybe along with that, I put onboard new OSS
contributors, right? Like, what is the impact beyond that? But also, and this is really
maybe your next talk, everywhere we do one of these, we should leave behind a thriving
IPFS community.
I put in a couple of points in there too. The ones that start with communicate is all
me. Because I think we seriously need to communicate better and about all the exciting stuff we
are doing. One insight, so I was talking to like developers from India, sort of preparing
like, what are their motivations, etc. Like trying to understand that. And one insight
was that, you know, IPFS was really cool when it started. And now it's just something that
the people who know about it use it like, you know, either through a pinning service
or like, but there are not a lot of people engaging with all the new developments that
are happening. So we need to do like, we need to be able to like communicate everything
that's happening better. And sort of similar to expand core protocol contributors is also
making sure we get, they know what to contribute to. So it'll be the roadmap for all the different
implementations that we have or the other projects that are being built in the ecosystem.
Okay. Is there anything else anyone would like to add to the goals here?
I mean, the one thing I'd note is that I find it remarkable just like how aligned all of
these are. They're very much in the same space. So I think that's a pretty good sign.
Yeah. I have a question on this one. Every attendee votes on IE awards.
So the impact evaluator awards were a vote that we did for, we did the first round of
awards at the last IPFS thing. And then we did the next round at this one and we had
people vote, but we actually had, given there was almost 150 people here, we had about half
that number of people actually vote. And I think, and maybe that's just actually a articulation
of a higher level goal, which is these events should result in community participation and
engagement in what the IPFS ecosystem actually is. And I think the impact evaluator awards
are a way for the community to participate in determining its own future and what gets
funded, what gets acknowledged, what gets rewarded for being created and that is value.
And there's a signal in there about how, is that set of things to be voted on the right
set of things? If there's low participation, then maybe we're not getting the right set
of things in there. And so I think there's that participation in that process is a really
good way of measuring the health of the community, showing how much the people that are putting
on these events and setting up those awards are in touch with what community needs are,
do we have the right people participating? So that I've just kind of threw that in there
as a, if we can get everybody who registers to also vote, then we might get a better sense
of some of those things. Yeah. And also I think it's an important way of
putting money where our mouth is. Like, I mean, very literally in this case, it's like,
when we say that we want community to drive this thing, it's like, well, here, here's
a pool of money. You go like, drive where it goes. I think that that's a very important
message to try to like get as many people to notice.
I have a, like, it's not a problem, but there is a difficulty in actually being able to
execute this because not everyone ends up looking at all the projects and the question
and the emphasis is on all the projects. So even if everyone ends up voting, like, how
do we make sure that if there's like a hundred projects submitted to this, how, why, what's
the motivation for people to actually look at them before they vote?
I mean, I don't think we should expect everyone to look at every project, but so long as the
way in which people get to see projects is reasonably random and they're not all exposed
to the same three projects that everyone's going to vote on. I think that's fine. Yeah.
Okay. Cool. So maybe a good way of like summarizing the goals and objectives. We can club these
tickies that are in the similar zone. I'll just like take 30 seconds to do that right
now. Okay. So it looks like grow the number of new developers in the IPFS ecosystem. That's
one goal. The left group of stickies. What's a good way of summarizing the second bucket?
Philosophy of IPFS deployment production group track. And yeah. Can someone help me here?
I don't know how to summarize this group. The second one. Oh yeah. This one.
In the middle? Yeah, the middle one. Like philosophy of IPFS, deployment production
grouper track and get more nodes running. Like what's a good way of...
I mean, I think philosophy goes with communicates, you know, on board. I don't know.
I put philosophy in there of like, you're like, this is what you do. This is what it's
about. This is the long-term plan. Every human on the planet can store stuff online effectively
for free, effectively forever. And then it's like, that's super exciting. How do I get
started? You should run a node. And they're like, okay, I'm running a janky little home
node or running IPFS desktop. But, and then it's like, oh, here's how you like run it
for real at the library or something is kind of how I was thinking about it. But why, how
and ouch. Yeah. Why, how and ouch. Can you note those tracks?
I'm actually going to write that down. I was serious.
Yeah. Okay. And then the last group is I think clear and simplified communication of our,
of the key takeaways from IPFS thing actually. Right? Okay. If we go to the next slide, that's
where I'm typing those down. Okay. Does this, do we, I mean, we can iterate again on this
later, but does this look good so far to everyone or is there something major we are missing?
And a great experience. The idli sambar goes there.
I think the objective ultimately is like activating India. Activate India.
Yep. Okay.
This hasn't really been in the camps in the past, but like, sorry, this hasn't really
been in the, in the, in the past, but what does it look like to engage with local civil
society, not just young hackers, right? Like what, what does it look like to connect at
the state level or the national level? You know, like if we're going to be flying a bunch
of people from around the world to there, are there some other discussions that we can
have face to face or showcase? That's like compliance, Robin.
Yeah. Yeah. Open question. I don't think you have to put it in an objective.
Okay. Let's actually, that's a good thing to discuss right now. Any other open questions
people have? Because I think it would impact the goals and objectives of the event. So
any other open questions? One is engage with the local community.
Oh, all right. Builders on versus contributors too. Yeah.
Yeah. 100%. And I feel like the other question there is within those two subgroups also,
is like how familiar someone is to IPFS and like overall programming, like experience
level, right? So our tracks have to be able to cater to either we, either we communicate
this is only for X type of folks or we program for everyone who turns up.
Okay. Okay. Let's look at the slide again and see if we are missing anything major.
Project India philosophy of IPFS. Grow the number of new developers in the ecosystem.
Simple and clear communication of key takeaways from IPFS thing and then a great event experience.
Okay. Okay. And I think with that, we can open to just like brainstorming on the content
we should have at IPFS camp. It need not necessarily translate into a track, but yeah, let's maybe
use the next slide. How much more time do we have? 15 minutes?
I think we have quite a lot of time. Okay. Okay. Yeah. So yeah. Next step, let's
read the objectives again. Add more questions if we think we have more questions. Oops.
Yeah. And yeah. And then let's start putting in ideas on the stickies in the next slides
on what we think should be covered in the content we do. So it's just like dump ideas
there like small, big, not great, great. All of them.
I had a bunch of different ones. Some are ones that we've already had. Like we've had
IPFS everywhere, but we didn't really focus on the hard and the why and why they're hard
and how to get there. So it could be that we have a new track about like, we kind of
called it integrating IPFS, covered some of that this time around, but I'm really focusing
on like a track about IOT or a track about mobile or not underwater really, but IPFS
in space as a track, right? Could be. And then I added another one, this track of doing
stuff with IPFS that might not even be technical. That might be using applications that support
IPFS. So people have this experience of, Oh, I made this thing, or I published this data
or like a group writing session where everybody publishes their, their, what they wrote on
the IPFS. So not necessarily coding, but actually using it, uh, IPFS as a user.
Okay. I also love the how to hold your own IPFS community events.
and I added like a superset track there next to that, like the train, the trainer, like how do we teach people to be better? Uh, speakers at events and train them how to do good decks for teaching how to code or doing their thing. I think those types of things really help energize and activate a community. So that could be under the like activate India. So that, that community leaves with a bunch of new skills about how to continue doing that work.
And a list of people who speak the native languages there. Right.
Um, yeah. Although you want, uh, like developers generally speak English, so I don't think we will face any language barriers. I mean, we did fill Bangalore last year and all the talks were in English and or the entire audience was like perfectly comfortable understanding all of it and interacting with the speakers. So I mean, it would be fun to know and to like, and hear some of the languages.
We could throw it in as an experience, but it's not like one thing that we do get though is that means that the people, the people that aren't English comfortable did show up, but it doesn't mean that people that weren't English comfortable, weren't interested in might've come.
Um, so one thing that we get requests in our, uh, localization platform, it's people request like IPFS companion or IPFS.io or docs, IPFS in different languages.
And so it could be that we have a localization track where, yeah, where people, you know, group together. If we come out with a group, a working group that say are the leaders of a given language, they're like, Hey, I'm the lead for Bengali and we will translate the docs website or the IPFS, the Helia examples repo or things like this into a language. Sure. Specs. Fine.
That could be part of the train, the trainers track to write just one of the call outs of action. It's like if you really care and you want to learn how to run a community event and you speak one of these languages, you know, consider being a localization resource, right?
It's one of those things that I actually care a lot about, although I don't do a lot of work on, but yeah, there's nothing cooler than to go to an open source event somewhere in the world and realize that you're in the room and you're giving a presentation in English and there's a group huddled in the back with somebody who's translating it in real time.
Like I've seen this multiple times and then they sit down and they're coding in their native language and that's when you realize you're getting outside of our little bubble.
Yeah.
That, uh, that gives me an idea.
We could probably have a developer influencers track or like group.
No, it's the thing.
Like there are, there are college students who actually have YouTube channels with thousands and thousands of followers and people follow them and I see Mohammed smiling there.
Do you know one of them?
Yeah.
So there are, there are like, um, people who do that.
That made me think about something else.
Like, what about accessibility?
Right.
Um, have we been thinking about that enough?
Cause like maybe even more so than, uh, cultural diversity.
I don't think we've been thinking enough about like different barriers for people who are disabled, like ASL.
Like what if we have developers who are hearing impaired?
How can we make sure that they can participate in, you know, the different events also for the show and tell talk to me.
I mean, you think about, um, like a maker's track, right?
And that could be a way to include a wider range of people who are not just developers into the space.
Cause I don't think as far as like creatives, artists, and people who could potentially make IPFS attractive and marketable are, um, a big part of the community right now.
It's like core technical people who are cool to us, but may not be interesting to the wider public.
So thinking about like just different wearables or IOT or digital art, different ways that IPFS could be integrated, it could be a way to get a bigger group of people into IPFS community.
Yeah.
A subset of that group is also designers.
I keep hearing from teams that are like building products, like we need good designers.
They don't come to Web3.
Yeah.
I mean, even when we're talking about, uh, NFT artists and making their own platforms, like to me, it would be great to have a whole talk on how could you build your own platform in IPFS, deploying your smart contract on FEVM, being able to, you know, retain a large percentage of your, um, margin, your profit margins for your art.
Um, I think that would all be interesting.
Um, yeah, I mean, it's just a lot, a lot of ways we can include a wider range of people.
Okay.
Um, I'll put it in the next slide.
Um, one track I would love to see, um, based off some of the talks I saw this year would be IPFS and privacy.
Um, specifically between, you know, fissions work on private and permission data on IPFS and the sort of reader privacy work in the DHT.
Um, I work with a lot of activist organizations at the foundation who, uh, you don't have use cases where they care a lot about privacy and, and potentially a lot of misconceptions about how private the network actually is, um, for a lot of their content.
Okay. Any other ideas?
This is the time where you imagine you have a magic wand and you can get whatever you want at IPFS Camp this year.
Okay.
I put in a few ideas as well on the second slide there.
Um, one was office hours, uh, with operators, uh, basically the community that is here right now, because I feel like talking to the community that is at IPFS thing would be a huge value add.
Like getting those one-on-one conversations, uh, would be a huge value add for like developers, uh, who are new to the ecosystem.
Um, all day dosa.
Yeah.
That's, uh, it's, it's illegal if we don't have that.
So.
Sorry.
I'm sorry.
Uh, I wanted to speak to the wind bounties and internships track.
So, um, no JS interactive conference typically does like they have bugs and issues that are printed out on little paper slips that they hand out.
Um, and then they have like a group of SMEs subject matter experts walking around to help people on like interacting with development, trying to solve actual bugs.
Like we have help wanted tasks out there and we point people there, but having that session interactive during the conference, I think would be really useful because a lot of people look at those issues and then are overwhelmed because it is overwhelming.
It's a huge ecosystem.
So I think that would be really cool.
Yeah.
I think that's a great idea.
Like plus 100 cool.
Yeah.
Okay.
Um, yeah.
And that's, yeah, I think I was trying to go for something similar when I say, I put up the digital matchmaking wall idea, like just like match open problems to build us.
Like, you know, imagine if there was a wall where you have a, like you could submit a problem and then somebody could be like, Hey, that problem is interesting.
I want to solve it.
Who do I find to be able to like solve it together to collaborate?
So yeah, I think, I think both these ideas can marry and become something that's very meaningful for attendees.
Okay.
For the digital matchmaking wall.
Like a lot of, a lot of times, like even at this conference, you know, we have the unconference where, you know, sometimes there's a little planning ahead of time.
Sometimes there's not, but it like is just all culminated, culminated into one single like timeframe.
I think it would be good to have that be persistent throughout the conference where you have that wall available at first day, all the way to the last day where people can say like, this is a problem.
Like this is a problem people can maybe put on there, like I am a potential solver of this problem and I am a potential potential, you know, beneficiary of this problem.
Like, so then you find all the groups trying to solve the same problem and all the people who might be able to solve that problem.
And then maybe provide, they provide their own contact info or like facilitate them getting in touch and actually meeting at some point.
But having that available the whole time, I think could be really cool instead of just like one on unconf that then ends.
Yeah.
You know, I think this wall is a good social graph idea, right?
Like you could just build an event app for this just to be able to like do this.
Okay.
And yeah.
I think it would just be like a Trello board, right?
A Trello board with like the different needs.
Trouble board.
Yeah.
And then just like different needs of startups or companies in the space.
And then as people want to pick up those needs, just pick up the sticky note and move it to doing.
And then you could like spin that up really quickly or it could potentially even be something that's like created on IPFS that's a reiteration of Trello.
Yeah.
Trouble makers board also sounds nice, right?
No, but I think that's a good idea.
Okay, cool.
Any other ideas?
I, one of the challenges in these events is oftentimes we're using software to do the event or to talk about the event or to talk to each other at the event that doesn't actually reflect our values or use our
stuff.
And I wonder if there's some like focus on, on a dog footing, like the, an outcome of, of the thing that replacing the things that we would otherwise use that aren't typing for us.
Like a decentralized Slack.
Sure.
Or even like a calendaring thing, or like you just said, an event app or, you know, something like that, but just that theme, not event specifically just for the things that we do every day.
Got it.
Okay.
Yeah.
So we have a lot of ideas here.
I'm not going to club them live right now, but would be great if people can just like, if throughout the rest of the event, you'd come up with like more ideas, just like dump them here.
I also want to maybe reflect on all the tracks we had last year and see if we want to redo some of them or not do some of them or do them differently this time.
So maybe we just like go track by track and comment on each track.
So the way we'll do this is possibly we pass it on the mic for each of the tracks, and then I'll just like make notes with everybody's comments on it.
So the first one is keynotes.
I think the objective slide.
Nah, cancel.
There's really a lot of tracks.
I'm wondering if like passing the mic around might be a pretty rough way to do this.
Do you want to do it the slide way again?
Yeah, that might be good.
And actually, because I think one of the things we probably want, and I don't know if we have the right people in the room for, is the track leads.
Yes.
Because they'll give the kind of like the retro on that.
So might need to do this one async.
Yeah, I think.
Okay.
Okay, then that just leaves the track leads.
I think if we have keynotes and browsers and platforms, we're good.
Thank you for that.
Some of the, I think a retro on IPFS thing would also be really good because some of these we did like computer over data and measurement performance browsers like data transfer, content route.
Actually, yeah, so far everything in the screen are also tracks we had here.
Yeah.
Okay.
So then, so then what we'll do is we'll just look at the retro we did yesterday once more and then come back with like a recommendation for async comments.
And then possibly also keep the like apply for a track option open, right?
Once we announce the event.
Absolutely.
That was one of the things that I was going to say is super important in order to meet the needs of the community of people that will be coming.
Yeah.
Is creating as wide a possible vector for that input as early as possible.
So a lot of these are kind of curated and specific to the core implementers and builders and don't really map to that larger audience.
Like I think it's fascinating that the list of track ideas that we did at the beginning is so far away from this list.
And that's, I think something that might be interesting too, from an organizer standpoint is asking the question, being really clear, what is the difference between camp and thing?
And so it's a very different audience and they'll have different needs.
I think there's an opportunity to bring a bunch more other organizations that have commercial offerings, their own protocols and a bunch of other things in here that isn't really represented necessarily.
And really like we want to invite people who are using IPFS as a platform and succeeding as a platform.
Again, we want to curate it, make sure it's like, okay, so what are you doing that's like actually connected to IPFS?
But we want to showcase that.
Yeah, absolutely.
In fact, some of those people, there are a couple of PLN, a few PLN companies based in India.
I am hoping to have them as like organizers.
So I'll be like reaching out to them to help us because it's going to be a lot of people.
We need a lot of local support.
So I think that's it.
Yay.
If there is anything else, please find me or Huni and like let us know if there's an afterthought you have at any point.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.