I'm Yuni and this is Nicole.
Hello.
And we are the MIWA team.
MIWA stands for Milky Way.
And we had this idea, I don't know, a few months ago to do something called IPFS and
Friends Cafe.
I think exact name TBD, but oh yes, we do want to make it bigger.
And really the purpose at the time was to tag on to larger events.
For example, East Denver.
And here you can see where we had our little IPFS and Friends Coffee pop up.
Our first one.
It was so awesome.
So we want to continue to do more.
And so we tagged on to the Filecoin Foundation Hacker Base and we were open for, was it just
one day?
Yeah, we were open for one day.
We were open like throughout the morning into the afternoon.
And we were having people come in.
We were introducing ourselves, having them scan this QR code so everyone scan it, kind
of get familiar with the link tree and what we're offering.
And we were also telling individuals there if they're interested in hosting an event
like this, that we would love to collect their information so they could do so in the future.
And not just this, like in the link tree we also have pre-registration for IPFS camp,
IPFS thing, the community events calendar.
And so really it's just to get more information about other people who might be interested
in coming or speaking.
But this one wasn't, there was no content surrounding this.
The idea really is to create like a, I want to say like a workshop or a cafe where we
can share ideas and we would be, yeah, collaborate.
And we would help a community member create their own cafe so that they can continue to
run it in their own little ecosystem or their community.
And so here's a map of the world.
I shared this link in the Slack channel, so feel free to join and we're going to do the
little heart game again.
If you can put where we should be hosting the community events.
We want to know where you think we should be, where we should go next, just unique locations.
And maybe if you have a recommendation of who could help host that, that would be great.
But I guess the first one can be in Serbia.
Yay.
Wherever.
There you go.
Giant, giant heart.
The giant heart.
Perfect.
And let's go ahead and put one in India.
Oh.
Where are we going in the US?
That's a big heart.
Yeah.
I love it.
That's Princeton.
There's a regular gathering of blockchain meetings, but they're like very, very narrowly blockchainy.
And I would like to change the minds.
Nice.
Yeah.
So you would be willing to host the cafe there?
At least once.
Yeah.
Okay, cool.
We just want to offer the resources to everyone and lend a hand.
Yeah.
South Africa would be amazing.
Yes.
No Australia.
I'll do it.
I'll go.
Yeah.
Do you want it in Utah?
Boris, where's your computer?
This is the struggle.
I don't understand.
I don't know.
So what are we doing to help you?
I'm having trouble.
Tell us.
I don't understand.
You can just tell us.
Tell us.
It's covering all of the possible locations.
Amazing.
We got it.
Cool.
Yeah.
So we will have-
Copenhagen.
Oh, Copenhagen.
Yes.
Are you hosting?
Oh, amazing.
Yay.
So cool.
Perfect.
We love that.
I'd say in the beginning, we could offer logistics.
It's really catered to your needs.
Like if you need logistical support, help securing PL speakers, we could provide you
with swag.
We can offer some small monies to help you secure a venue or something like that.
And then once you guys have done it once or twice, then you can be off into the world
and you know how to run your event.
But any kind of advice or anything like that, we can help support you.
Did I forget anything?
No.
I think that's it.
Yay!
Did you want this?
Yes.
And you can read this if you want.
So some of the goals of this IPFS Friends Cafe would be to grow the IPFS community events.
We don't really have that many going on.
And so I think this would be a great way to get them involved.
Build a calendar between IPFS Camp and IPFS Thing.
Those are the two main events that we have going each year.
So people are always asking, when's the next thing?
When are we going to see everyone?
So this would be nice to supplement in between.
And obviously keep up the momentum.
We just want to keep going.
We want to go further and wider.
And this is the way to do it.
And we'll see you soon.
Thank you.
Any questions?
Is this a mini...
Is this a full-time job?
I like IPFS and Friends.
It's very friendly and you could have a number of things on the Friend side of the thing
while sticking with the IPFS Thing.
Love it.
And even just some of the consistency of like, oh, this is what you can expect from this
sort of thing.
Do you see this...
Is this scaled down to local meetup?
Yeah.
And what do you see as the sort of main topics or things?
Is it an evening meetup?
Is it a side event?
You said speakers.
Yeah.
It can be.
I feel like what would be nice is if someone is interested, depending on what they want
to do.
Because I think the person who has interest has something in mind.
So if they want to do an evening event, if they want to do something with speakers, they
want to host a game night, if they want to do...
Just to get the community together, technical or non, I think that's the more important
part.
And we'll help them.
What are your thoughts?
Dietrich?
I was going to say, one of the event series that I loved was called Music Hack Day.
And Music Hack Day was like what you just described, Nicole, was exactly what was cool
about Music Hack Day, is that there was no centralized organization.
It was if somebody wanted to host a Music Hack Day, they just posted a pull request
to the Music Hack Day website, and the people that started Music Hack Day would either reject
it and be like, this has nothing to do with music or whatever.
But if they're okay with it, and there was just a community of people that had held a
few of these before that were the people making the decision, would just add it.
And it was just a title and a location and a date.
And so each one was really unique, and oftentimes they started repeating.
So like Music Hack Day Austin would happen a bunch of times over because that community
of people formed around that one thing.
And each one was then also really different.
And it reflected the interests of that local community in a way that also didn't have to
be a meetup group, and it didn't have to sign up, and it didn't have to put the official
name or logo.
But it could just be wherever they wanted to be, which was kind of nice.
Very flexible.
So I think that sounds really cool.
The way you described it sounds awesome.
Thank you.
Are you interested in DeFi companies, Hyperledger, people like that as well, tying up with them?
Yeah, if people want to sponsor, if people want to come in and collaborate, that would
be amazing.
Because in London, there's quite a bit.
Friends.
There's a big community in London that you could probably reach out to around this space,
the whole blockchain space.
Perfect.
Yeah, bring IPFS to them, I think, would help their platforms.
Please send us those recommendations.
Yeah, let us know.
Could we use these events for dogfooding stuff?
Yes.
Like force people to use our stuff?
Yeah, absolutely.
That's what it's for.
Like I want to keep the content flowing in between IPFS and IPFS Camp so that we have
something to present at these two major events.
So yeah, absolutely.
Thank you.
Awesome.
Any other questions?
No?
Well, thank you.
Thanks.
Thanks for being here.