HELIO & PERFORMANCE
OK, Helio & Performance
How to wring the most out of your deployment
This is going to be a fairly demo-like talk
If it gets dry, there's all these little sweets on the table, you just throw them at me or something
Keep it interesting, you know
OK, so it's me again
You'll see I've moved from being the JSI Professor maintainer to being the Helio maintainer
Things move fast
JavaScript is slow, right? It's super slow
I mean, it can be, if you use it badly
There are things it's really bad at, like CPU intensive tasks, awful, or worse
Don't do it, if you can help it
Async, also terrible
Async is not free
We have to remember this
This is a picture of the browser event loop
I'm not going to go into it in very much detail, there are loads of really good resources out there
The really important thing to notice is when you're calling browser APIs and you see it says promises
And there's a little line, a tiny little line, oh by the way I'm going to add something to the microtask queue
So every time you invoke a promise, an item gets added to the microtask queue
This is incredibly expensive
When you're doing stuff in a very hot loop
You really don't want to do it unless you absolutely have to
And I think we, like promises have a lovely API, just like await a thing, that's great
But then actually it can be really really bad
So how bad, so a quick demo of how bad it is
Where's my thing gone, there it is, ok, ah it's again
So what have we got, we've got itpipe
So it uses a lot in JS, everything
It basically is for making pipelines of operations
It all just takes an async iterable and just turns it into a list
So these modules have recently been refactored quite a lot
So I say it takes an async iterable, it takes an async iterable or it takes an iterable
If it takes an async iterable it returns a promise of the things
And if it takes an iterable it returns the things
So now these things are actually promise aware
Which is pretty handy
So we've got a synchronous pipeline here
So all we're doing is, we're having a list of numbers, five numbers
We're just going to iterate over the source, iterate over this list, increment them and yield them
The output of the first function is passed into the next function
And so on and so on, and at the end we just collect them all together
So we've got a list of five numbers and we've got five transforms
Five transform functions and then a sync at the end where we just collect them all
That's the sync one, and then the async version is exactly the same
Exactly the same, the only difference is we've just stuck the async keyword on
Which we do a lot, oh yeah async, no problem
So you've got the async keyword on there, we await the constant of the list
Note that the list input is still a synchronous list, it's just an array of numbers
So we do the do all the way and then just collect it at the end and then await the result
We don't have to await the result here because the whole thing is synchronous
Node Perf1
So we run the benchmark, bang, and you can see the difference
So the number of operations per second is 132,000 operations per second in the synchronous pipeline
And then 81,000 operations in the async pipeline
So it's an order of magnitude slower
And all we did was put the async keyword on things and await
So async is not free, definitely not free
Storage, storage matters
How am I doing for time by the way?
12 minutes, ok right I'm going to have to start speaking really quickly
Ok, ok, well it'll be nice if it gets back on track
Anyway, storage matters
CPU is boring in JavaScript, but I.O. kills everything
Like it doesn't, a lot of the time it doesn't matter if your algorithm is the fastest or not
Because every time you hit the network or the file system or whatever it just blows it all out of the water
An enormous bottleneck, so you have to think really carefully about the block stores that you use in your application
This is something that actually bit us a while ago
One of the users opened this bug that the S3 performance was really slow
And there's this tiny little, tiny little thing in the Amazon documentation
It says your application can achieve at least 3,500 operations
Or whatever, per second per partition prefix
And a partition prefix is basically a forward slash in the bucket path
What it doesn't say there is that if you don't have any forward slashes in your bucket path then it's one partition
Which means that your entire bucket can achieve at the maximum 3,500 operations per second
Which is awful if you're scaling
Really bad!
And then also, if you create 10 prefixes you can do 55,000 reads per second
Which obviously if you see that it was 5,500 and suddenly it's 55,000 with 10 prefixes
What's 5,500 times 10?
It's like, oh okay, right, that's a fairly linear thing
I wish you told us about that in bigger writing
So now the S3 block store has learned from this and applies a default sharding strategy
Of just taking the last two letters of the path, reversing them and sticking them on the front
You can shard, obviously there is a limit per prefix
So if this prefix isn't long enough for your application
You can override these settings when you create your block store
You should measure everything before making decisions
Other data stores are available
So we have these two modules, block store core and data store core
And they include implementations of a whole bunch of different types of block store and data store
And they're not always stores, they don't always keep the information
Things like mount data store I think is very interesting
Perhaps something that has massively unrealized potential for performance
All your data and blocks, in particular the data store, they're all accessed by keys
And the keys have a very predictable structure
So that means that you can say with absolute certainty that certain classes of data are stored with certain keys
So you could treat, for example, peer store data as ephemeral
Because the network changes a lot, you join, you leave
If your peer ID changes, suddenly you have different peers that are close to you
So maybe you don't actually care that much about the peer store data
So if you had a mount data store and you just used a memory data store for the peers prefix
Then all of your peer data would just live in memory
And then when you shut the node down and start it up again, you haven't persisted disks
But you also haven't, aside from the async tax that I just went through
You haven't hit the disk at any point or hit a network or a database or anything to actually store this information
So it could, like if you see a lot of peer churn, this kind of thing could make your application massively faster
The same way with some blocks, if you want to ensure that some blocks are very fast to fetch and others you want to store cheaply
You could put them on S3 or you could put them on Glacier Storage or whatever
Go nuts, like this is a toolkit, you can build this
Tid data store is another one, so the way this one works is it wraps a whole bunch of different data stores
And if you write, it will write to all of them and if you read, it will read from whichever one is fastest
So maybe you would have, you know, like Web3 Storage for example
Races a bunch of gateways against each other to fetch a block
You could use something like this, and there's the abstraction for you
And then like, you know, they would just pull it from whichever one is quicker
Maybe you could create your own, like the hot content block store
Like, I know this CID is going to be massive, it's going to blow up, it's my new album, it's incredible
So I'm going to write a data store that stores that CID in memory
Like the blocks that make that CID up, stores them in memory, so they're super fast to retrieve
And everything else can go to the, you know, the slow storage
It's up to you
Content reading, so content reading is really slow in general
Like there's just no way around it, because it involves network requests
So if you're searching for content, you have to hit the network
And hitting the network is slow, regardless of the language
So one thing you can do is you can configure delegates
So these are different implementations of content reading
And like JSLickP2P will try them all
So some of them are fast, they're streaming
IPNI, of which there are some talks about this week
You should totally go and check them out
It's novel because it has a streaming API
So the ones that don't have a streaming API
They return a JSON object that has a list of providers for a given CID
But there's the whole list
And once you get to the end of the list, there are no more
And the list is wrapped in a JSON object
Which means that the slowest provider to arrive
You get it at the same time as the fastest provider to arrive
So generally you want to go for the ones that have streaming APIs
So IPNI has a streaming API, whether or not it's streaming on the back end, I don't know
But it has the capability for this
The non-streaming ones reframe
And then the old school delegated content reading
Which just hits the KubeRPC API
Pinion garbage collection
So we care about this
This is more like an internal thing about how Helia works
But in the olden times, in JSRPFS
We switched from using a DAG
So the list of pins that you had on a given node
Used to be stored in a DAG
And you used to have to manipulate that DAG
Which involved hashing things and all that kind of stuff
Which is CPU intensive
And if you remember from this very first slide
CPU is awful, don't do it!
So what this one does instead
Is it stores all the pins in the datastore
And the datastore is very fast, particularly in JS
And so what this graph is showing is
As the number of pins that you have
The time it takes to add a pin goes up and up and up
That massive spike is caused by the DAG that we had
Going to another level
So we'd filled one level of the DAG
And then we started a new one
And then suddenly the number of calculations that you have to do
To recalculate the root CID and that kind of thing
Massively goes up
Which is why you see that enormous jump there
And then the red line at the bottom
Which you can barely even see is the datastore
The datastore performance
Which is massively better
And this is the time it takes to add a pin
So you've got the old JS implementation on the top
You've got Go in the middle, so that was Kubo
And then the new one
New one
Is the red line at the bottom
Like massively faster
And this is the number of pins that you're storing
And the time it takes to store the next pin
So this is 100,000 pins in the datastore
And it's kind of flat
Which is what you want out of a refactor like this
So it's much more scalable
And that was just the
I'm going to go back one
So that was just the
That was putting pins into the datastore
But it doesn't tackle garbage collection
Which historically has always been super slow
Until, until now
So Helia runs reference counting
For its pins
So it's a very simple idea
That's the PR that it landed in
Super simple idea
You
It has a benchmark suite as well
Which is what I'm going to talk about next
But yeah, it's a super simple idea
Every time you pin a DAG
You walk the DAG
To ensure that all the blocks are present
Every time you encounter a block
You keep a count of the number of times
You've seen that block in all of the DAGs
You increment it
And then when you unpin
When you unpin a DAG
You walk the DAG again
And you decrement that
Every time you
Every time you encounter one
And then when it comes to running garbage collection
You just look at the counts
And you're like, does anything have a count?
Okay, you're safe
If not, you're gone
Which just makes it much quicker
Because then you're
You're basically deleting the blocks
As fast as you can pull the pin counts
Out of the database
Which is a lot faster than
Walking a massive DAG
So what would previously happen is
You would walk every DAG of every pin
And you would say, right, these blocks are safe
And then you would walk every block
And say, is it in that set of blocks?
If not, then delete it
Which is enormously expensive
Whereas if you're just pulling stuff out of the datastore
It's much quicker
So here's what happens
So this is the number of blocks
That have been pinned along the bottom
And the number of milliseconds it takes
To do garbage collection
And so cubo is the red
And helia is the blue
And you can see that helia is much faster
And as it gets further and further away
It gets bigger and bigger
I mean, this is what you want
Totally what you want
Got some other useful stats out of it
So this is how you
When you're unpinning things
With helia it's super quick
Because you're just doing some database stuff
You're not really doing a lot else
Cubo does a lot more work
When you're adding blocks to the block store
I mean, adding pins
This is the good one, right?
Adding pins is just flat
Much faster, much, much faster
And also this is what happens when you
Instead of just blindly copying
The algorithms that cubo has works for cubo
And it works for Go
And it doesn't work for JS
Because JS is terrible at CPU
Whereas this approach doesn't use CPU
And so consequently it's much faster
So you write algorithms
That are sympathetic to the environment
That you're deploying them in
Not because of the algorithms
Last section, DAGs and bit swaps
So bit swap is slow, it's really slow
I mean, Ian's talk in the keynote
He alluded to
If you have sensible data structures
It's not necessarily slow
Which is completely true
So what is a DAG?
I'm just going to go over what a DAG is
I was going to use the DAG explorer
But it's really sad at the moment
It doesn't work, which is a shame
Because it's really lovely
If someone would like to PR effects to this
Maybe with helia, that would be cool
Anyway, so I robbed this from some IPRD documentation
So what is a DAG?
It's a graph
It's a directed acyclic graph
Which has an interesting property
In the way we do them
At least you don't know what's
If you have to load another layer of the DAG
You don't know what's there
Until you've loaded it
Which takes a long time
Which is slow
And that's what we don't want
So what that means, essentially
The interesting fact is
Every time you go down a level
You're incurring a performance penalty
So maybe don't do that
So again, here's some benchmarks
These ones are quite interesting
There's a pull request
It's not fully formed yet
But please do check it out
Anyway, so
What I did here was I changed
I was changing the
This is our bench line, sorry
This is the kubo defaults
Which jsipfs inherited
And you can see the
The size of the DAG along the bottom
And the time it takes to transfer
Between two nodes
And they're all kind of like
Yeah, it's interesting
So Helio is actually somewhere up here
Which means there's some low hanging fruit
I'm sure in bitswap
And what I did here is I increased the block size
So instead of having 256 kibibytes
It's now 1 mibibyte
And you can see the numbers on the left
So the top here is 150,000 milliseconds
And then the top goes down to 100,000
So there's significant speedup
Just by making the block size bigger
Now the interesting
One of the interesting things about this
Is Filecoin uses 1 megabyte block sizes
And there's already
I mean look how fast kubo
So kubo is here
The kubo2kubo
To transfer 1 gig in 256 kibibytes
And now it's all the way down here
So like these things really matter
And you should totally benchmark
The kind of data structures that you're creating
As just some stats
So Helio with 256 kibibytes
Goes from 10 seconds to 7
To transfer 100 megs
Kubo goes from 8 seconds to 2 seconds
Which is, you know, massive
So when people say that
Bitswap is slow
Maybe it's not
Maybe it's the data structure that's wrong
These things can definitely be optimized
That's it
So the important thing is to think about stuff
Don't take anything for granted
We need to measure things
And think about our data structures
And no nice abstraction is free
Definitely not in JavaScript
We should definitely make things better and faster
Thank you
That one needed more emojis
I meant to ask after the last talk
But is there a certain channel that you hang out in
Where people can find you on Slack or anything like that?
You can just add me anywhere
So I've been trying to be more on the IPJS channel
Cool
But yeah, you can just add me anywhere
Good, good