Hi everyone! I see a lot of faces from last year, a lot of new faces, some faces from
IPFS Camp 2022, but we're here to announce the dates and the location for IPFS Camp 2023,
which is going to be November 3rd through the 5th in Bangalore, India.
We're super excited, and if you take a photo of this QR code, it'll link you to our pre-registration
page along with some other links in there. So go ahead and pre-register to stay up to
date on all the news and updates. Yay! Super exciting! Nikki's going to talk a bit more
about India.
Hi everyone, I'm Nikki, I lead the Hackathons program at Protocol Labs, and also coordinate
India-related initiatives. I just wanted to give you a little bit of a background on why
India for IPFS Camp. So according to GitHub, 2.5 million out of the 20 million new developers
they got in 2022, 2.5 million are from India. And by 2025, 10 million devs would be from
India. And in one to two years, the highest number of web 3.0 devs globally would be from
here. It's a country with 1.4 billion in population, and 60% of them own a smartphone, so that's
like a huge audience that is available to scale IPFS and distributed web.
We also had an amazing experience last year at India Blockchain Week in 2022. We did Phil
Bangalore, which had 1,300 attendees. We have a very strong community, Hudlo1, which is
a PL network company built on top of Lippie2P and Filecoin. They organized Phil Bangalore
for us, 1,300 attendees, all of them really strong developers. And we also were a big
part of ETH India, which is a hackathon by ETH Global. And the India hackathon was the
biggest hackathon they had done till date, with 1,750 hackers, 2,100 total attendees,
and 450 projects were built in those two days. So yeah, we got great energy, and India is
like full of developers who want to solve really hard problems in networking. And yeah,
I look forward to doing a few initiatives with all of you before we do IPFS camp so
we can get the India community going. Please come find me and talk to me if you would be
interested. Otherwise, I will definitely come find you. Thank you.