All right, well, welcome to the integrating IPFS talk, or track. This track is kind of
like a grab bag of a few different talks that didn't quite fit into other tracks, or maybe
a few smaller tracks that got combined together. So this is kind of our schedule for today.
I'm going to open us up with the first talk, are we interplanetary yet? David will be next.
He's going to talk about DURN, which is IPFS on mobile. And then Brooklyn will follow after
that with decentralizing Auth and UCAN, too. Then we'll have a little lunch break, and
then Arakli will come in with a UCAN workshop. And that's slated for 90 minutes, but he's
just going to take as much time as he needs to within that to talk us through that. And
then we'll have Brooklyn again talking about IPVM. So this is kind of like the Brooklyn
and other people show. That's kind of what this is turned into.