My name is Dietrich Ayala. I lead the Browsers and Platforms team at Protocol Labs, and it's
my pleasure to kick off IPFS Thing by answering a question you all probably have. Why does
this event have such a weird name? Last year, we had the very first one of these in Iceland,
home of one of the oldest parliaments in the world, where for over a thousand years, the
council elders have been gathering to make decisions and talk about the most pressing issues
affecting their people. Likewise, when this guy, Juan, articulates a vision of digital
human rights that resonates with us, we gather now annually to chart the course forward for
the IPFS protocol itself. So the work that you're doing when you're building with IPFS,
when you're filing bugs against the protocol, when you're giving feedback in the specifications,
that important work, thank you very much for participating in this event to help determine
where IPFS goes from here, to be able to meet the needs of the internet that needs it very,
very badly. This is an important mission for me, after spending a significant chunk of
my life trying to make a better web, but still finding ourselves in a place where you can't
do something like share a photo with somebody inside your own house. Without that photo
leaving and going through the hands of 38 different for-profit companies, we would like
to see a different future, and your participation here is making that possible. With almost
double the size of IPFS in 2022, you being here is what's going to make IPFS able to
achieve the vision that we have for the internet and the web that we want to see. So thank
you very much for attending. We have three days of talks in the core tracks, followed
by two days of mostly open time for you to gather, work together, collaborate, meet new
people, and build the internet that you want to see in the world. The event is almost entirely
going to take place on this floor of this building, which should make it very, very
easy for everybody to find anything. Some of you are probably going to get lost anyway,
but there is a bunch of breakout rooms. We have the three main rooms with the tracks
in them, a bunch of rooms that you can use to be able to self-organise, find your people,
help them find you, and make the things that you want to make. The seventh floor also has
breakout rooms for people to use that have probably a nice view. I haven't been up there
yet, but worth checking out. For logistics, if you haven't checked in already, check in,
get your badge. Here's some Wi-Fi information with a very creative password. The last couple
of days have a lot of open time. There's a lot of rooms. There's an unconference sheet
shared in the Slack, in the general channel. Sign up there, broadcast what you want to
do and what you're interested in doing, even if it's not set in stone, so that the people
that are interested in that can join you and you can do amazing things together. Dinners,
the evening events, the system is very simple. You received a slew of emails from Luma. Go
to those emails, click that you accept and join. That way we know you're coming, and
then you get to eat with friends. Otherwise, you're going to be on your own, but that won't
be as fun as hanging out with us. We're going to be going to a bunch of different places
around Brussels. It should be a blast. Make sure you go into Luma and click all the yes
things here if you want to join. Join the Slack. If you're not there already, we will
be using the Slack for every important announcement for the duration of the event. Please watch
that. There's channels for each one of the tracks as well. If you want to talk to the
community of people that have shared interests in that track, that's the place to do that.
You can find all the speakers, ask questions to the track leads, get all the information
there, and then at the end of the week, we will take the Slack and make a little effigy
of it and burn it in the hopes that next year at IPFest we have something IPFest-based that
we can use instead of Slack for doing this. This event is under the IPFest community code
of conduct. Please be excellent to each other. Also, we are in a place known for its amazing
beers, so please intake in moderation and keep an eye out for folks that may or may
not need assistance and help. If you need assistance from any of us, please reach out
to me, Boris from Fission, Nicole, who I'm not sure are in the room, but they checked
you in at the registration desk. Those folks and also this email address where all of us
organizers are there. We're here to help. Just reach out if you need anything from us.
Thank you to everybody who participated in making this event happen. These events happen
through the hard work and many, many months of planning across a number of different organizations,
protocol labs and a bunch of companies outside of it all participated in making this happen.
Thank you to all of these folks. Please give them a big hand.
Your track leads in particular have done a ton of work to be able to create a very engaging
and quite full list of talks for each one of these tracks, so please be very appreciative
to the people that are leading the tracks in each one of the rooms and all the speakers
that have put a bunch of work into their talks. This is going to be a short morning with a
really lot of information packed in. We have a long series of talks for this next hour
and we will fit a whole bunch of them in in a very short period of time, followed by a
couple of very important and exciting announcements for you all. Thank you for coming to IPFest
Thing. I really appreciate you being here and your commitment to making IPFest as best
it can be to meet the needs of the Internet we all want to see.
So with that, I would like to hand it off to Yanis, our first speaker of the morning.