So, you know, since this is about community, we figured it would be a good idea to start
off on some kind of kind and gentle note.
So I assume people here are familiar with what a postmortem is.
Postmortem is when something has gone wrong and you get together after the thing has gone
wrong to discuss what went wrong.
And one thing that people often find out when doing a postmortem is that we knew that something
was going to go wrong, but either someone had figured it out but hadn't shared it well,
or someone could have thought about it but hadn't really believed that things were going
to fail as badly.
So it turns out the knowledge that something was going to fail usually exists before the
thing fails, unless it's a catastrophic surprise accident.
That's how it usually works.
So the purpose of a premortem is to actually try to figure that out before it happens.
The idea is really to get rid of optimism bias by projecting ourselves into the future,
say 10 years from now, noticing a failure and then going like, okay, it failed.
Why do we know from today, but, you know, retrospectively with the hindsight of 10 years
in the future, how do we know that this was going to fail?
And so, you know, I'm not saying that the ones that we listed are like the three only
failure modes.
I think that the idea is to invite people to sort of like think retrospectively that
way to try to figure out what might be wrong and what we should do about it today before
it actually goes wrong.
But I think one thing that's pretty clear is that if, you know, 10 years from now, IPFS
has failed, it seems unlikely or implausible that it will be for lack of technical excellence.
I think we've all seen, you know, of course in the community, but, you know, even more
clearly in the past few days that this is an absolutely excellent community at the technical
level.
And even though there are issues, I think we're very confident that they will be conquered.
However, we can imagine cases in which IPFS will have failed.
So let's imagine it's 2033.
And you know, these are just like three example potential premortems to think about.
But the first one is IPFS has succeeded, you know, to some degree, but it has been captured
by some big tech company or other.
So, you know, pick your least favorite one.
And they are basically for all intents and purposes owning IPFS.
And you know, in the same way that email and large parts of the web today, despite being
technically or supposedly some degree of decentralized, are, you know, captured and owned.
And so, you know, that's the failure mode for that first one.
If we look back, you know, what has failed to lead to that failure mode?
Well, one way of thinking about it is that perhaps we didn't think of capture resistance
sufficiently well.
We you know, there's a tendency in our community to imagine that if you make something decentralized,
if the tech is decentralized, then everything will just go well because the tech is decentralized.
But you know, the people who work to capture markets don't go like, oh, that tech is decentralized.
That's unfortunate.
Let's just like go monopolize something else.
You know, you have to get into a cybersecurity mindset about this and like really threat
model the hell out of it, because they will keep coming and they will find an exploit
and they will eventually monopolize something.
And so, you know, we need to build sort of the community culture of thinking not so much
in terms of decentralization, even though that's an important technical property, but
in terms of capture resistance so that we keep ourselves honest in terms of whether
we're succeeding on that front.
So that's one failure mode.
A second potential failure mode is the one in which, again, IPFS is maybe even super
successful, but it is entirely a Protocol Labs product.
Maybe we pretend that there's some kind of community and we take input, like we have
like developer events and we're like, yes, we listen to you.
This is very important.
We will consider it.
But it is actually completely owned by PL.
And this is a failure mode because this is supposed to be locked open.
This is supposed to be a common sting.
And how would we reach that kind of failure mode?
Well, if we don't take the steps to develop institutional capacity in the community to
properly own things and to properly govern things in a way that is open, then we could
easily progressively slip into that mode, even with good intentions.
And we've seen that happen over the past decade in tech.
And so a third failure mode is actually in this case.
So this is the one in which IPFS actually almost doesn't exist anymore.
And the thing that has happened is at some point there was some kind of absolutely catastrophic
usage of IPFS for some major phishing or some horrendous CSAM network or something like
that.
And the reason that happened is because we as a community didn't take the steps necessary
to integrate into the broader institutional ecosystem and play by its rules and actually
support people in building good things.
So again, this is a third case in which the failure is a failure of community and governance,
hence why we're here.
So now that I've...
Yes?
Do you want to ask?
Can anyone mention other failures?
Yes, this is going to be a participatory session, so you should expect not to sleep in the back.
How else do we fail?
Speak in the mic, Boris.
We can fail at delivering the decentralization bit.
We can be just smoke and mirrors at some point over time, adding more and more centralized
pieces of infrastructure.
So on the website, it may say we are decentralized, but if you shut down, like Amazon goes down,
suddenly content routing does not work.
I'd say that's a failure mode that should be on the list.
HTTP with extra steps.
Inefficient HTTP should not be synonym for IPFS.
That's a good one.
Anyone else?
So I think that was a really good one to capture.
Addy has one.
Can you wait for the mic?
Yeah, sorry.
I'll run it.
It's okay.
Is it working?
Yes.
I was going to say something around complexity or obfuscation and complexity, so we lack
mainstream adoption, especially outside of the West.
Yes.
Oh, look, everyone has failures now.
Keep the sharing coming.
It's a plus one on what Addy's saying.
Yeah, like poor product market fit.
Yeah, sure, we're open source and we scratch our own itches, but we really have to stand
back and say, is this a G-Wiz project?
Like, oh, great.
We actually have an interplanetary file system.
It's on satellites.
It's on Mars.
Cool.
Nobody uses it because it doesn't really solve a problem, right?
Because there's like infinitely easier, faster, simpler ways to do the same thing.
So there's a tendency for nerds to nerd out, right?
And we need to constantly check ourselves.
We used to do this at Mozilla.
It was like, oh, we could totally do that in the browser, right?
We can totally do that.
Yeah, we can remotely start a car using a browser.
But should you, right?
That's the question, right?
That's a failure mode is to not step back and say, should we do this enough?
And also that means that we need to be bringing people into the community who provide checks
and balances against groupthink.
Yep.
Does anyone else want to be pessimistic this morning?
All right.
Well, thank you.
Thank you.
No, this is definitely very good input.
So in terms of like thinking about it, and again, like I just picked the three that we
thought about, but like the ones that you brought are also important.
Based on this kind of like premortem exercise, we can figure out the things we want to build
and why we want to build community and governance capacity to provide these checks and to provide
this input and to keep ourselves honest and on track.
And so, you know, this involves like really figuring out how to avoid capture, how to
build collective action, and how to play well with others.
Those are like really important institutional aspects, aspects of governance.
And I think from all those that we heard also map one way or another into this, right?
If we have ways of like getting real community input, and that's not just like a call center
input, but that's actually people have voice that translates to action.
I think we can avoid a lot of these issues because that's how we are smart together.
So you know, in terms of like, do you know why you should be afraid of the French?
Because they eat pain for breakfast.
So things we would like to get out of this workshop session today are we'd really like
to get an idea of the pain points regarding governance of the IPFS ecosystem.
I mean, a lot of you are involved in it.
When you are involved in it, what is painful for you, but also what is painful in terms
of the people who aren't showing up or the support you're not getting or things that
you've, everyone has been saying, yes, we should be doing that for five years.
And it still hasn't happened.
That kind of painful.
Oh, I see Lidl's face.
I think I like struck a chord right there.
We're going to talk about browser extensions.
Every community goes through this, right?
So we can just like enumerate these things, but we can also solve them.
And one thing also is that is, you know, doing governance well and right is something that
is very much an art and hasn't been developed into very much of a science yet.
And so like sharing ideas and thoughts and best practices about how to do it well is
also something that we'd like to invite today and in the future.
I think very specifically, no pain, no gain, meaning we actually have to practice governance,
which means we will also sometimes fail at governance.
And what we have to do is learn from it so that we can get better at it.
I mean, you know, in real world governance is always absolutely messy and chaotic and
horrendous.
And so, you know, like, yes, we'd gain for breakfast because no, wait, that doesn't work.
And so, you know, we want to basically use this to strengthen the ways in which we cooperate
and work together and like work with other institutions and the broader community.
And so, you know, just like as some open ideation issues, the list is actually longer.
Of course, we'll get to a longer list right afterwards.
But you know, one of the questions, some of the questions you need to think about when
thinking about governance in concrete terms in terms of like how to make it happen is
like, what is it that we're governing?
Actually, what are the resources that are in the commons?
Is it the open source code?
Is it the standards?
Is it the infrastructure?
Is it the community culture?
It might be all of these things, but it's good to have a clear idea of what it is that
we're actually managing through this governance process.
There always has to be a resource, right?
You're not just like governancing for the fun of like having meetings, right?
The other way, the other important thing is like which actors, you know, in terms of like
specific positions in the community, like people who use it, people who code on it,
people who might have, you know, opinions about things, people who write, who create
logos, I don't know, like different roles, like which of these actors do we like to see
taking which roles in terms of governing things is also an important thing.
Like who gets to have maybe more say over some parts, who gets to have like a specific
kind of input into this or that kind of resource.
And then based on this, like how do we organize these to achieve the goals that we want to
achieve?
And so, Boris, do you want to jump on the parking lot a bit?
Live up here?
Yep, you're live now.
Live, live.
Awesome.
Yeah, so this was a bit of a parking lot pointing out to some different areas.
We've got one area that Robert and I have prepared and almost given a little update
of sort of some emergent stuff that we see happening.
We've got about 15 minutes, we've got five minutes in, so I'd like to take 10 minutes
and basically go through some of these things so that we can start gathering this as a list
of like, oh, are we just going to come and talk about it here or is this something that
we're going to kick off and be like, how does this flow into other events and meetings and
other things that we have over time?
Standards.
What does that even mean?
I wanted to put that up there to kick things off because I think we do multiple kinds of
things.
We do standards that might be happening at the W3C or the ITF that I guess sits in Dietrich's
and your hands.
Is that correct?
I mean, kind of.
The ITF section is being discussed.
So the ITF is, it looks like ramping up a multi-formats working group, but that is just
for multi-formats.
It's not this tiny fraction of the stack.
But we do need to get our act together in terms of like finding chairs for it, figuring
out who's going to edit the specs, provide input.
At the very least, we need people to review the specs and help with that.
But that is one section.
But then there's the, what do we do with all the other specs that we have or that we should
have or all the parts of the stack that exist but don't have a spec?
Do we just like get LIDL to write all of them?
Or do we develop a system where...
I've been told that if I stop fucking around with mascot shaped stickers and just buckle
down and make hexagon shaped stickers for UCAN, then like it'll just automatically be
part of the IPFS universe.
Is this true?
Okay, great.
Okay, done.
Standards equal LIDL plus stickers.
Right.
Yeah.
Okay.
Fantastic.
And I think, yeah, just putting that down there because there's standards, standard
quotation mark, like it's both something that we shouldn't be afraid of being like, oh,
let's do a pattern of writing stuff down.
And again, some of that might come out of a hack project where we have something that
works and then, oh, we want more people working on it.
And this tension between I wrote some open source code and cool, can three or four other
organizations implement it because they like crabs better than gophers or whatever reason
they might want to do it, sort of thing like that.
And part of that can be like expectations, right?
So for instance, it's not perfect, but when a browser vendor ships a new technology that
they haven't even sort of like slightly contributed to the standards process, people scream at
them.
It doesn't stop them completely, but there's a cultural expectation that if you're going
to add a feature, you should at least like pretend to have a spec and give it to the
community, which is better than not even bothering.
And I don't think we have that muscle developed yet.
I think we don't want to stop people from coming up with ideas and trying stuff out.
But if you're going to add a significant feature and put it somehow in public where it's going
to be used by people, it's probably a good idea to develop the expectation that it should
be at least the outline of some kind of markdown spec and we make it pretty easy for people
to write specs.
So I think that should be an expectation that we grow to develop.
Thoughts, pains, delight around this word standards.
You should add this into your threat model for capture because I've seen so many open
source projects who started at the standards place and suddenly Microsoft comes in and
is like, oh, we're building Ion, right?
We're going to do this thing you call decentralized identity.
And since this group has not actually written a spec, there's no reference implementation,
we're going to push this standard in a direction that makes it only Microsoft who can do it.
So I think the one thing to keep in mind is we have a lot of technical advancement already.
We have a lot of specs we still need to write.
Look at Lidl.
He literally just said we should write some more specs in the previous meeting.
But anyway, there is this tension of do we implement it first and then write it down
and show the world that this solves a problem and this is what we're going to do?
Or do we go to the standards body and incorporate feedback as we design?
There's always tension there.
I think the rule of thumb is yes for protocols, no for implementations or no for anything
that would be considered implementation detail.
And that's where something like the decentralized identity and the CCG working group just went
off.
They went down the rabbit hole of all these little implementation details.
And I don't know that anybody uses CCG standards much.
We have tiny little bits of dits here, but they have all kinds of problems because of
it.
Maybe like potential mitigation here is to not just write text, not just write prose,
but also have a system when it's needed.
there's an expectation of having a working code with your spec proposal, kind of like reference implementation.
And then as a part of the ratification process, have expectation of some sort of a test suit that's vendor agnostic.
And we are trying to prototype a process like that for the gateway specs, where we have expectation you, there's a spec.
So one thing you need to have a spec, then you can have IPIP's improvement proposals, deltas against the spec.
And when you want to propose a change, you come in with code and then as a part of ratification process,
you are expected to also bring test fixtures to this vendor agnostic test suit.
For the gateway, it's fairly easy HTTP. For other things, it may be more tricky,
but I think this is a forcing function for people from the wider ecosystem to get an early warning where there's a capture attempt.
Because the moment I'm not able to like test it with the provided fixtures because it relies on some centralized thing
or some proprietary thing that I'm not able to implement because of patents or whatever.
That's the early warning. That's the time when you have a warning before you ratify the spec, before it gets like too far.
I agree.
You know, that's a good point. I mean, it's certainly true that defending against capture in standards is a problem
that we sadly have a lot of experience with based on the W3C, for instance.
I do think that ties to a broader discussion about how to organize the community and what happens when things start to become successful
and how do you scale your governance to match success.
A lot of the time you see projects that begin and the governance is basically just norms.
You have norms of how you're supposed to contribute and how you're supposed to participate.
And that's great so long as no one's income relies on it and so long as it's not too successful.
You know, like I don't want to do a thing that will make Boris angry at me, so I do the right thing.
But at some point it becomes big. Like my income depends on it.
And if it depends on doing something that makes Boris unhappy, well, maybe that makes me sad, but I'll still do it.
And then you get something that falls apart and that is easily captured because you need to go from norms to rules
and something that has a lot more enforcement capacity in it.
I wanted to point out actually, that's an excellent proposal of talking about that process.
Who funds that?
The infrastructure contest or the people who are...
Wait, wait, Mike, Mike, Mike, Mike, Mike.
I'm an indie hacker who would like to do a new thing.
And I can't possibly do all of those things as the first step.
And I don't think we should even dig into it.
This is the prompt of like, that sounds awesome.
So I can get some contributions to get all of that stuff done that's not me, the indie hacker or other things like that.
And this is some of the tensions of where some of this lives and what base infrastructure is.
To what you were saying in terms of the diff and other things like that,
what we really found is I think the ITF model of rough consensus and running code is a good starting point.
We went to the diff.
We'd done a bunch of early stuff with DIDs and we went there and did a demo for them.
They're like, oh, wait, this is working?
I'm like, yes.
And then we got into some discussions.
We found a lot of people there had thought a lot about identity and a bunch of other things like that.
But it was theoretical.
And so we didn't actually have a partner to do, for instance, interop testing with where the expectation was kind of like,
well, we'll write it all down, including some of us who had written code.
We're like, that is not going to be useful to implement or hard to implement in code.
So some of those tensions were, I would say, almost there.
Like, I start very early on in saying, I guess, intent to implement is sort of a thing that I almost,
it's just something that I know lots of people who are more into the W3C are twitching when I say that phrase sort of thing.
But I'm like, could we use some patterns and say, oh, I'm going to stick up my hand.
Yes, my org group, individual indie hacker would also like to run, deploy or code X.
And that kicks things off of saying, like, it's not just a single entity as an example.
Yeah. And I think, I'm not sure if that's where you're going, but I think parts of the standards,
it's like specs plus framework of testing that it's not, there's like no lock in around this test framework.
So the thing is, yet another example of the gateway conformance tests, we are prototyping the entire,
like the design decisions that we wrote down was, everyone, we should be able to run this on the canonical place
where people can compare implementations.
Then each implementation, it can run it in their own infra.
And then every end user could use it to empower themselves and verify products that provide gateways.
So the test capture and making sure it's locked open and not tied to a specific implementation is very important.
We struggle with that because the gateway implementations right now are mostly PL driven,
but through the project, we are in other places, we are able to, like,
at least we have multiple implementations with different limitations.
So that's a starting point.
And tests are a good way of getting community participation because, you know,
hackers can easily like go like, oh, this is a test suite.
I understand how this works and I can contribute something.
And in general, I've seen quite a bit of success in standards worlds where you make it easy for people to contribute tests
when they find a bug.
And they do because it's a great way of getting other people to fix the bug and to do the work for you.
So that is a helpful vector for sure.
So we've gone deep on the first one.
What I'd actually like to do is do a speed run of adding a little more color to each one of these things mean,
and then also just getting a kind of show of hands of which of these things are interesting that we might dig into.
Because a lot of these are just prompts for us to be like, oh, right, these are some people who are interested in this stuff.
Let's keep talking about it.
So network operations, and kind of put bad bits in there directly to say what Robin said about, like, oh, you know,
we don't want the main IPFS commons network.
Does anyone, I call it main net, borrowing from blockchains who have this concept.
And so an open question, is there a label for the main public reachable IPFS commons network?
Oh, that's like an open slot.
We are looking for a name for DHT.
But now it seems that we also need a name for the entire network.
So we need two names.
And logos.
Do we need two names?
Because do we need to name the DHT separately from the?
I don't know.
There was a proposal to call it Baba Yaga yesterday.
Plus one for vilification.
Literally.
Awesome.
That's really, that's really.
So, and then there's the actual network operations where some of the stuff that Rob and I have been looking at in the decentralized data compliance group
that we'll talk about this afternoon is like, okay, real companies that are registered in real countries are going to run real servers
as part of stuff that they run and where they operate those things, they have compliance needs.
Hey, instead of everyone having to do this all by themselves, can we cooperate and help each other out
so not everyone is starting from scratch,
including some shared compliance things around which bad bits we might not be allowed to serve.
So this is a guard as a community against the vilification.
Yep. Yep. Right.
And I think we're seeing the IPFS operators group kind of reboot and that'll hopefully kind of find a home in there.
But they're probably not that not the same set of people who are looking at compliance.
So like that.
I mean, the two work together.
But yeah.
Open source governance, a placeholder that is more about the code and goes into in the current model that we have,
where lots of code gets written by PL.
What is PL's approach to saying to taking feature requests or taking PRs or not taking PRs?
There's a bunch of different ways to do this and what this looks like.
Some of it is once again tied to funding as a form of power that you have to think about as well,
which is why I have that one as the next thing.
We have a bunch of things in motion.
There's an IPFS fund being formed.
Addy, is that going to be talked about here?
There's more than one.
There's more than one?
Okay.
Is that on the schedule anywhere?
There was a little bit touched upon in the keynote.
So we have two sort of divergences.
We have one that is the traditional IPFS fund, which I'm dubbing the Web 2.0 version.
And then we're building out a Web 3 version, which is all on chain.
So it's like based off of staking mechanism and pooling on GILF.
And then those will be fractionalized using quadratic voting or some kind of weighted voting scheme with governance
so that everything is on chain and essentially trackable and traceable for both the community and the funders,
with the idea being that the funding will be completely decentralized so it's not coming from a single entity.
And the hopes there is that we can then fund and allocate money to higher risk, higher reward projects.
So I don't know if that answers the question.
But there's sort of two tracks right now that are going in parallel.
That's amazing.
Like, again, this entire track is a honeypot for people with information and people with questions, right?
So even though like, oh, we need two names for the thing, we're having it recorded.
So this is the kind of thing where I'd love to follow up and be like, where do we go to follow along, find out more?
What is the Filecoin Slack channel or, you know, hashtag on Blue Sky to follow or whatever?
So that's awesome.
Thank you.
Evangelism and Ground Game.
So that's something that Yuni wants to cover a fair bit this afternoon and she's not here yet.
In a couple of different ways, which is, again, so to what you were saying in terms of like, it has to be useful to people generally,
which might start with cool technical hack that incites a community to keep going and sort of thing,
but then has to transition to exactly what Eddie was saying about like, hey, how about we use some languages other than English
and think about places other than the Western world?
I had an amazing discussion with some Mayan activists at IPFS camp, and they told me a little bit of like,
once we translate it into our language, here's some of our thoughts on how IPFS is or is not connected to some other things
and how it makes us feel.
And I'm like, super interesting, right?
So all of these, like, we have to do all of these things to some degree.
And some of this is like, great.
So there's these two parts of governance is in part the like, who decides or who prioritizes?
And community is the, in part, great.
How do we work together and do some collective action around it instead of just single individual or single org?
Yep.
I was just going to point out that the cool thing about the open source governance and evangelism and ground game,
and to some degree funding, these are well-trodden paths, right?
There's been a lot of success in the last 20 years for, you know, like Mozilla, Linux Foundation, lots of these.
And then, you know, even the IEEE is really good at this.
And so I think we should make sure that we go at this not thinking we're going to make a PL-flavored version of it.
I think we should definitely maybe organize a conversation around doing like a SWOT on what Mozilla did or what Linux Foundation did.
And pull from them, like learn from the people who have come before us.
Because we certainly have something to add to this.
You know, what Addy's talking about, you know, cutting new paths into Web 3 funding and how do we do voting?
And how do we do everything on-chain and transparently?
But to get there, right, there's so much we're going to need to do that has already been figured out.
So let's not spin our wheels on that. Let's work on, you know, the cool stuff that we can add.
Your laptop did not like staying.
Yeah, completely agree. I mean, two examples come to mind there.
Not necessarily fully successful, but that have interesting properties at least.
One is Wikipedia developed a pretty serious, like, ground game.
And everyone knows how bureaucratic and complicated it is to actually make Wikipedia function.
And that was a key part in getting an entire community to understand a very complex set of rules to build governance around a shared system.
That, you know, maybe bureaucratic, maybe difficult and painful, but generally works more than it doesn't.
And the other is ISOC, where they manage a pretty significant budget annually.
And I think it's a very significant chunk, maybe half, at least a third, possibly more than half of the budget is managed by ISOC chapters.
And so I'm not convinced that the community representation they have is very representative.
But at least they figured out a way of doing this kind of collective budgeting.
I actually 80% disagree with almost everything that you said.
Here's what I've seen having practiced a bunch of this stuff 20 years ago when open source was still a radical act.
I think those orgs figured it out from the early 2000s to today.
What I'm seeing is essentially open source 2.0, where a lot of people have come up without it being radical
and don't actually know how to practice.
Another point is you said PL. I believe you meant PLN, of course, right?
This is a problem that we generally have in the N part.
We don't talk about the N part, in part because of point four of funding where most of the locus of that lies.
I think a lot of the new stuff coming from Web 3.0 is super new and no one really has it figured out.
And there's some new techniques in there, right?
So how do we split these things and go double down on the things that we know that work that might target certain types of orgs?
Or I actually see that a bunch of those techniques work in the global northern west
and pretty much don't in the global south and southeast Asia.
And that's really the arc of, oh no, the Internet is now worldwide
and our ground game actually has to be global and not just English-centric, right?
So I'm not disagreeing, more saying, yes, and.
What I was thinking about is exactly what you were saying.
If you had me write down a list of the things that I admire from previous organizations,
I think the people who know anything about Mozilla would say the one thing they are really good at is translating.
They have all their documentation and all their educational material in like 80 different languages.
So I agree with you, Boris.
I'm not trying to be sort of like the global west-north-centric.
In fact, there are some things about some of these organizations that are so good about the global south
and getting it into places.
The IEEE does a really good ground game with institutions, educational institutions.
They're like a PhD factory.
And there is so much of what we're doing that it has open-ended questions,
like things that could fuel and also fund a lot of research.
And so anyway, that's what I'm thinking.
I think you and I agree we're saying the same thing.
I'm not thinking like, oh, you know, let's throw giant parties in New York City.
I'm thinking let's –
I'm not against it.
I'm not asking you to make a rule that's like a law.
My vision here is having a presence on the ground pretty much everywhere in the world
with people who are speaking in a native language and teaching people how to build with this.
That's an amazing mission statement and I think very good for UD's session.
Thank you for pushing back, though.
I love it.
Of course, we're over time now.
Let's quickly flip through the working group.
So having gone through –
one thing that we wanted to bring forward here is that there's this sort of like novel idea,
that novelish idea that's been floating around and where people are sprouting up working groups here and there.
And it's great because we should be working and in groups.
So you figured out that that should be a good idea.
But the purpose of working groups is to get us cross-organizationally to figure things out,
and they can have different types of approaches to different things.
Some of them are much more like pragmatic solving things.
Others are like let's organize towards a mission.
But we haven't really formalized this in any way or figured out what are the rules
and what does a working group need to be.
So I think we should be thinking as a community about what do we expect from a working group
and what should we bring into working groups.
And so there are basic building blocks like it should have a charter, it should be there for a purpose.
It should also know from the start when it stops to exist because you don't want these things to just live on forever for no reason.
They should have some communication channels that are where the community will expect to find them.
Today, if you wanted to find out all of the working groups that exist around the IPFS thing,
I have no fucking clue how you would go about it.
I'm not even sure that if we put all of our brains together in this room, we would succeed in listing all of them.
I think we'd probably forget some. There are probably some that we just don't know about.
Well, you have access to the secret V2 notion where all of this information is stored, don't you?
I thought that was in the secret V3 notion.
That was a PL joke from someone who's on the outside.
None of this should be shocking or particularly revolutionary, but this is basically how it's done
and the kind of thing that we should figure out how to normalize and have a list of them, for instance,
and how maybe they could share a code of conduct and stuff like that.
And so this brings the question that's always horrendous, is do we need standards for standards?
And the answer, sadly, is usually yes, much as you want to punch yourself in the face as you say these things.
But we probably need a working group working group of some kind.
Not that it should be an intensive amount of work. Ideally, this should be a very lightweight affair.
But some group that basically sets out these things. When do you start a new one?
Where do we put the list of all of them? What tools should they have? And that kind of stuff.
How do you announce and promote your working group so that it's not just you and the friends you met at the bar last night
who had a great idea, but also other people in the community who might be interested?
And really, the idea is how do we make this an effective structure that people can get off the shelf,
use to solve a problem, put back on the shelf when the problem is solved, and not become some big bureaucratic nightmare.
Moving on now, Enrique, what we're going to do next is, so we've got a channel in IPFS Slack.
I will take a bunch of these open things and some of the notes that I captured and tag some names of people,
get a HackMD up so that we can use that throughout the day for some of these other things,
along with communicating with all the speakers, which I did not do ahead of time
because we were running a little late in the massive atom in the sky last night.
That's great. This is recorded. Thank you very much. Enrique is up next.
Thank you.